A Guide to the Thomas Nelson Page Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8641-q
Thomas Nelson Page Collection 1836-1952
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8641-q
29 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift 1990 August 6
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Farcical poem entitled "Dutch Marriage Ceremony," unsigned but addressed to Virginia Lafayette Nelson, n.d.; AMs, 2 p.
- Letters
  - Subseries A: Letters of Thomas Nelson Page and Associated Letters
    - Thomas Nelson Page to Elisabeth Gilman, 1911 Aug 4; ALS, 2 p.
      [Re Robert's ( Robert W. Nelson) health and plans to attend school.]
    - Thomas Nelson Page to Elisabeth Gilman, 1912 Sep 6; ALS, 1 p.
      [Encloses cheque for $200.00 for two Nelson boys' tuition, apologizes for including her in the business transaction.]
    - Thomas Nelson Page to Elisabeth Gilman, 1913 Jan 3; ALS, 1 p.
      [Encloses cheque for $250.00 for the Nelsons' tuitions, is glad to hear they are doing well.]
    - Thomas Nelson Page to Elisabeth Gilman, 1913 Feb 17; ALS, 1 p.
      [Encloses $200.00 for balance on tuition.]
    - Thomas Nelson Page to Elisabeth Gilman, 1913 May 23; TLS, 4 p.
      [Suggests that it may be time for Robert to go to work, recommends that Gilman discuss the matter with Loulie Bruce, explains that he has many calls on him and enumerates one from his cousin who cannot send his son to school.]
    - Thomas Nelson Page to Elisabeth Gilman, 1913 May 26; TLS, 1 p.
      [Recounts conversation with Louise B., his sister-in-law, concerning Page's ( S. Page Nelson) eligibility for St. Paul's School; does not promise to continue his financial support, but agrees to keep the matter under his consideration.]
    - Thomas Nelson Page to Elisabeth Gilman, 1913 Jun 7; TLS, 3 p.
      [Agrees to send the tuition if Gilman writes him that only through his assistance can the Nelson boys continue their schooling, says that he would like to be kept abreast of the two boys' activities in the future.]
    - Elisabeth Gilman to S. Page Nelson, 1939 Dec 27; TLS, 1 p.
      [Encloses two letters from Thomas Nelson Page. ]
    - S. Page Nelson to Robert W. Nelson, [1947] Mar 17; ALS, 1 p.
      [Encloses photographs, says he has found other boyhood memorabilia predating the sale of Banister Lodge and will divide other pictures with Robert.]
    - S. Page Nelson to Robert W. Nelson, 1952 Sep 17; ALS, 2 p. w/env
      [Encloses Thomas Nelson Page letters, expresses gratitude for Lizzie's ( Elisabeth Gilman) having stood by them; discusses presidential race and possibilities for banking if the Democrats stay in, calls for depression to weed out competition.]
  - Subseries B: Letters of the Nelson Family
    - [ M. M. Elfreth] to Virginia Lafayette Nelson, Oakland, [1843] Sep 13; ALS, 2 p. w/env
      [Wishes good health for your Brother Robert, sends materials and 56 cents change, sends regards to various family members]
    - Robert Nelson to Hugh T. Nelson, 1884 Apr 17; ALS, 4 p. w/env
      [Has written to Dr. Mallet and Col. Venable, hopes he may get the place; describes a wedding in New York from which he has just returned; says he has received a letter from Dr. Mallet, a copy of which he encloses; Mallet recommends Robert Nelson for one of two positions as Instructor in the School of Mines of the University of Missouri. ]
    - Horace Jones to Robert Nelson, with two additional letters on same leaf, [1887] Nov 15; ALS, 4 p. w/env
      [Jones encloses note for $10 payment of Nelson's bill, reports on having visited the Oakland household; Nelson writes his mother ( Virginia Lafayette Nelson), reports on family news, sends along Major Jones' letter; Hugh T. Nelson writes his mother ( Virginia Lafayette Nelson) about family matters.]
    - Robert Nelson to Virginia Lafayette Nelson, 1904 Oct 4; ALS, 2 p. w/env
      [Discusses family news.]
    - "Your affectionate old Aunt, E. K. Page" to Virginia Lafayette Nelson, 1909 Aug 9; ALS, 6 p. w/env
      [Mainly discussing family news, with mentions of the St. Martin's Parish day (a church holiday with a sermon by Virginia Lafayette Nelson's kinsman, Rev. Everard Meade, and a paper read by Berkeley Minor), John Page's appendicitis, Mary Willis Minor's stay at " Rock Castle, " one of the Fontaine homes.]
    - Virginia Lafayette Nelson to Robert W. Nelson, 1947 Dec 23; ANS, 1 p. w/env
      [Note on an envelope which contained something given to Virginia Lafayette Nelson by her Aunt, Eliza K. Nelson. ]
    - Virginia Lafayette Nelson to Mr. and Mrs. Robert W. Nelson, [1948] Dec; APS, 1 p. w/env
      [Christmas card]
    - Miles [Farrows ?] to "Bob" [ Robert W. Nelson], n.d.; ALS, 1 p.
      [Says he is glad to give Robert W. Nelson the use of his rooms while he is away at Hot Springs, Virginia. ]
    - "Your affec brother" [in law, Robert W. Nelson] and "your... sister, Ellie C. Nelson" to "My darling Ria" [ Maria Clark], ALS, 3 p.
      [Discusses family matters.]
  - Subseries C: Letters of the Gilman Family
    - Charles J. Bonaparte to Elisabeth Gilman, 1910 Nov 21; TLS, 1 p.
      [Witty letter regarding Gilman's anticipated visit to " Bella Vista" and a hunting permit for her companion.]
    - F. Courtney to Everett Wheeler, 1911 Nov 24; ALS, 1 p.
      [Thanks him for suggestion of incorporating Kipling's Recessional in his next sermon.]
    - Rep. William Sulzer to Everett Wheeler, 1912 Dec 13; TLS, 1 p.
      [Thanks him for suggestions.]
    - Mayor William J. Gaynor to Everett Wheeler, 1913 Feb 24; TLS, 1 p.
      [Briefly discusses the three scamps.]
- Photographs
  - Included in a letter so dated from S. Page Nelson to Robert W. Nelson, 1947 Mar 17
    [3 unidentified and 1 of Robert W. Nelson clipped from newspaper.]
  - Included in a letter so dated from Virginia Lafayette Nelson to Mr. and Mrs. Robert W. Nelson, [1948] Dec
    [1 unidentified, 1 of " Banister Lodge, " 1 of "EAC" [ Elvira Ann Clark], 1 of "MBC ( Mary Bailey), EAC (Mother), MWC ( Maria Wilson, Aunt Wye)."]
  - Miscellaneous photographs, n.d.
    [2 of EAC [ Elvira Ann Clark], 2 unidentified.]
- Miscellaneous
  - School reports of Virginia Lafayette Nelson from the school of "The Misses Nelson" at Long Branch, 3 p., 1836-1840
  - Obituary clippings for Elisabeth Gilman, 6 p., 1950, n.d.